Guide to the Henry H. B. Chamberlain papers, 1863-1898
Chamberlain, Henry H. B. papers, 1863-1898
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry H. B. Chamberlain papers, 1863-1898
4274
Henry H. B. Chamberlain, ca. 1835-1877
.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, personal papers, documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence with family members with extensive description of Civil War involvement, and other miscellaneous family papers.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Primarily letters written 1864-1868 by Chamberlain to Mary Jane Field of Bridgeport, Connecticut, whom he married in 1864. Includes detailed letters to her written while he was serving with the New York Volunteers 97th Infantry Regiment and a diary kept from 1863 to 1864 recording his participation in the battles of Pollocks Mill Creek, Va., Petersburg, Va., and Welden Railroad, Va. Also, letters with detailed descriptions of his capture at Gettysburg, his internment at Libby Prison in Richmond, and his subsequent escape and return to action. Letters from after the war, written while he served with Alexander McDowell Cook and the 26th U.S. Infantry on the Texas frontier, include colorful descriptions of military life along the Texas border. Other letters include one written by Chamberlain to his mother; one by Captain Charles F. Dibble to his niece Mary Field (with a postage stamp); and a few to Chamberlain from friends and relatives. Papers include a marriage certificate, commissions - including one signed by Andrew Johnson, discharge and pension papers of Anson B. Field (probably Mary's brother), a quit claim deed, and probate documents.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Chamberlain, Henry H. B., ca. 1835-1877.; Johnson, Andrew.; Chamberlain, Mary Jane Field.; Dibble, Charles F.; Field, Anson B.; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 97th (1862-1865).; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 26th.; Libby Prison.
Subjects:
Gettysburg (Pa.), Battle of, 1863.; Petersburg Crater, Battle of, Va., 1864.; Family--New York (State)
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; Texas--History.; Texas--Description and travel.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Box 1
Series II. Family Papers and Correspondence
Box 2
Series III. Documents
Mapcase
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, April-May, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, June, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, August, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-Oct., 1864 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Nov., 1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 2-16, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 21-31, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jan., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Feb.-March, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, June-Aug., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-Oct., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, June, Nov., Dec., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Jan., 1868 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Feb., 1868 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, March, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, April, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II. Family Papers and Correspondence
  - Henry and Mary Chamberlain Papers, 1877-1898 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Charles F. Dibble to Mary J. Field, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anson B. Field Papers, 1864-1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers and Correspondence, 1864-1893 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Diary of Henry B. Chamberlain, Jan., 1863-Aug., 1864 (Box 2)
- Series III. Documents
  - Commission: Capt. Henry B. Chamberlain, 1863 (Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Marriage: Henry B. Chamberlain and Mary J. Field, Oct. 11, 1864 (Folder 1)
  - Commission: Henry B. Chamberlain - 2nd Lt., 1867 (Folder 1)
    Singed by Andrew Johnson
  - Probate document: Mary F. Chamberlain executor of the estate of Henry B. Chamberlain, 1877 (Folder 1)
  - Probate document: Mary F. Chamberlain executor of the estate of Anson B. Field, 1895 (Folder 1)